

Viacheslav Barinov

Moscow, Russia ☑ rayslava@gmail.com rayslava.com

Brief description

My major activity – C/C++ development on Linux-based platforms.

I really enjoy the OpenSource software and interaction with community and do my best to contribute to OpenSource projects which I'm interested in or have to deal with at day-time job.

Commercial Projects

C/C++ / Linux

Tizen https://tizen.org

Tizen toolchain support and enhancement.

Our team is working on toolchain support and enhancement accordingly to requests of Samsung developers all over the world and own vision of perfect toolchain. We are the guys who created an ARM64 Tizen 3.0 in the beginning of 2014 and stabilized the OS even before first 64bit Android release, and started RISC-V version in 2023.

Digging inside GCC and Binutils to find why stack trace tells lies to developers, debugging on-device soft using gdb through port forwarded using netcat over Wi-Fi because kernel is not finished and there is no other way to connect, finding a way to implement needed feature the right way instead of workaround in the limited time-that's about me.

After promotion to project lead the task set widened with looking for appropriate customer for such experience and directing team members' fun into scope needed by commercial divisions. Six years of successful projects say I'm not totally useless in this field as well.

Our team was invoked into code analysis movement and I joined dynamic analysis forces to improve and promote sanitizers among Samsung. Now, as far as I know, we're the first team who performed full-system sanitization (not sure if someone tried that anyway).

Experience

2021 - still Staff Engineer, Samsung Research Russia, Moscow, Russia

here Rust evangelism among SRR developers, research projects on new ARM and RISC-V platforms

2017 - 2021 Staff Engineer/Team Lead, Samsung Research Russia, Moscow, Russia

Toolchain improvement, dynamic software analysis research, Improving Tizen code base from toolchain point of view: dynamic analysis (sanitizers), new optimizations. Applying dynamic binary analysis technologies to embedded systems (Tizen RT)

2014 - 2017 Leading Engineer/Team Lead, Samsung Research Russia, Moscow, Russia

Toolchain support and enhancement. Improving Tizen code base from toolchain point of view: dynamic analysis (sanitizers), new optimizations

2013 - 2014 Leading Engineer/Team Lead, Samsung Research Russia, Moscow, Russia

Toolchain support (GCC compatibility issues maintaining and bugfixes)

Solving architecture related issues (porting from arm to arm64)

Feb 2012 - Software Engineer, Samsung Research Russia, Moscow, Russia

2013 Native mobile software optimization (C/C++)

Profiling and optimization tool development (Linux kernel module profiling part, python GUI and statistical and reporting module)

Software development.

Sep 2006 - Expert Engineer, InterRadioService LLC., Moscow, Russia

Feb 2012 Hardware engineering

Software development (mostly for hardware support).

Maintaining compatibility features for ancient (40 yrs and more) devices.

Fieldwork with hardware and support during full-scale tests.

Development skills

Programming Languages

Expert C, C++

Intermediate Rust, Python, ARM Assembly Language

Basic Perl, x86 Assembly Language

Frameworks and tools

Development Build system related tools: Makefile, m4, cmake, shell scripting, the GNU tool set built around traditional *nix software development.

Debug Low-level system debug: gdb, kdb, U-Boot debug

GUI Qt (C++ and Python versions), basic web-interface

OS Linux-based (from LFS and Gentoo to full rpm-based Tizen)

VCS git, svn

Server administration skills

OBS Deep knowledge of service internals, have experience in setup, configuration and bootstrapping from scratch for rpm-based Tizen OS

General Setting up and maintaining all servers needed for work – CI, source hosting, web-interfaces just need enough time.

Publications

Software Analysis

2020 2020 Ivannikov ISPRAS Open Conference, https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/ 9394129

Report Applying compiler-based binary watermarking technology to ensure binary compatibility in GNU/Linux distribution.

Published in Proceedings of 2020 Ivannikov ISPRAS Open Conference (ISPRAS). DOI: 10.1109/ISPRAS51486.2020.00009.

2019 GNU Tools Cauldron, https://gcc.gnu.org/wiki/cauldron2019

Report Annotating std::string with AddressSanitizer

2017 GNU Tools Cauldron, https://gcc.gnu.org/wiki/cauldron2017

Report Applying GNU GCC Address Sanitizer to whole Linux distribution

2017 2017 Ivannikov ISPRAS Open Conference, https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/ 8273297

Report Applying GCC-Based Address Sanitizer Dynamic Analysis Technology to Tizen OS.

Published in Proceedings of 2017 Ivannikov ISPRAS Open Conference (ISPRAS).

DOI: 10.1109/ISPRAS.2017.00015.

Education

2015 People Management, http://www.luxoft-training.com/, Moscow, Russia

Project manager tasks related to grouping people into team

- 2014 **Project Management**, http://www.luxoft-training.com/, Moscow, Russia Project manager quickstart
- 2005 2011 **Electronics Engineering**, Bauman's Moscow State Technical University M.Sc. in Electronics device and systems engineering

— Public activity

LinkedIn https://linkedin.com/in/rayslava

GitHub https://github.com/rayslava